<chapter id="webissues.prep">
  <title>Preparing the system</title>

  <para>In order to use the WebIssues system, it's necessary to configure a server which is its central and most important part. This chapter describes a step-by-step process of installing the WebIssues server and preparing it to work. If you use an already existing server, you can skip this chapter. For more information on updating the system to a new version refer to <xref linkend="webissues.admin.updating"/>.</para>

  <sect1 id="webissues.prep.requirements">
    <title>Requirements</title>

    <para>You can install WebIssues server software on a computer with Unix/Linux, OS X or Windows operating system. Before installing you will need the following components:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>A web server</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>A database server</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>PHP</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>You can use the Apache web server that runs on almost all operating systems (version 2.0 or later is recommended). You can also use the Microsoft IIS server which is part of Windows (version 7.0 or later is recommended).</para>

    <para>One of the following database servers is required:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>MySQL (version 5.0.15 or newer)</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>PostgreSQL (version 8.0 or newer)</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Microsoft SQL Server (version 2005 or newer)</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>In order to install the system, you must create a database on one of these servers and a user account with sufficient permissions to create tables and indexes in the database.</para>

    <para>In case of MySQL, support for the InnoDB engine is required. In case of PostgreSQL, the database should be created with Unicode character encoding. The SQL Server database can only be used if the WebIssues server is installed on Windows.</para>

    <para>The WebIssues server also requires PHP, version 5.2.1 or newer, integrated with the web server. In case of IIS server, to get the best performance it's recommended to use the <literal>fastcgi</literal> module and the <literal>wincache</literal> extension. PHP must also have the <literal>mbstring</literal> extension installed and enabled in <literal>php.ini</literal>, and if you're using a MySQL or PostgreSQL database, also the <literal>mysqli</literal> or <literal>pgsql</literal> extension, respectively. In case of a SQL Server database, since version 5.3.15 and 5.4.5 of PHP, the <literal>com_dotnet</literal> extension must be enabled.</para>

    <para>If you're installing the WebIssues server using an external web hosting service, make sure that it meets all these requirements. To create a database and configure the web server, use the tools provided by hosting provider and refer to the available documentation.</para>

    <warning>
      <title>Warning</title>
      <para>Some hosting services may have a specific configuration or other restrictions which make it difficult or even impossible to correctly install WebIssues server. They may, for example, limit the amount of available memory, the database size, or the size of files uploaded to the server.</para>
      <para>Installing WebIssues on a server with the <literal>mod_security</literal> module enabled may cause problems. Depending on the configuration, it may prevent the Desktop Client from accessing the server or block legitimate requests containing certain words. It is recommended to disable <literal>mod_security</literal> completely or disable the rules that cause problems. For more information, please visit <ulink url="http://wiki.mimec.org/wiki/WebIssues/Installation"/>.</para>
    </warning>

    <para>Before installing the WebIssues server, install and configure the necessary components, and then create a database using the appropriate administrative tools. Refer to the documentation of these tools to get more information about them. More information about creating databases and configuring the web server can be found at <ulink url="http://wiki.mimec.org/wiki/WebIssues/Installation"/>.</para>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="webissues.prep.installation">
    <title>Installation</title>

    <para>After ensuring that the required components are installed and configured, and creating the database, you can proceed to the installation of the WebIssues server itself.</para>

    <sect2 id="webissues.prep.installation.files">
      <title>Copying files</title>

      <para>Download and unpack the WebIssues server package &mdash; it contains a directory named <literal>webissues-x.y</literal> (where <literal>x.y</literal> is the version of the package). Then move all files and subdirectories from that directory to the root directory of the web server. External hosting services typically use the FTP protocol for copying files to the server, so you'll need an FTP client.</para>

      <note>
        <title>Note</title>
        <para>It's possible to install WebIssues server along with the other web sites and applications operating on the same computer. You can install the server in a subdirectory located in the root directory of the web server, as well as on a virtual host or in a virtual directory. Refer to the documentation of your web server or hosting service for more information.</para>
        <para>You can also create multiple separate instances of the WebIssues server in a single installation. Individual instances can be accessed through different domain names or subdomains, or in different virtual subdirectories. For more information, please visit <ulink url="http://wiki.mimec.org/wiki/WebIssues/Configuration"/>.</para>
      </note>

      <para>Then make sure that the web server user account has write permission to the <filename>data/sites</filename> subdirectory. To do this, use the file manager or the FTP client, or run the <literal>chmod</literal> command from the command line. A configuration file will be created in this directory during the installation. Also files attached to the issues will be stored there.</para>

      <warning>
        <title>Warning</title>
        <para>Make sure the <filename>data</filename> and <filename>common/data</filename> directories are protected from unauthorized access from the web. Otherwise it will be possible to download attachments without proper authorization. If you're using Apache, you can use the <filename>.htaccess</filename> files which are included in the source package for that purpose. For more information, visit <ulink url="http://wiki.mimec.org/wiki/WebIssues/Installation"/>.</para>
        <para>After the installation, also make sure that the WebIssues system configuration file is protected against unauthorized access, since it contains the username and password used to connect to the database. This is particularly important when using public hosting services.</para>
        <para>To ensure maximum security, it's recommended that configuration files and attachments are not stored in the <filename>data</filename> directory, but in a different location, outside the root directory of the web server. More information about changing the location of the directory containing these files can be found at <ulink url="http://wiki.mimec.org/wiki/WebIssues/Configuration"/>.</para>
      </warning>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="webissues.prep.installation.setup">
      <title>System setup</title>

      <para>Now you can open the homepage of the WebIssues system. Launch your favorite web browser and enter the URL of the server, for example <literal>http://www.example.com</literal>. You should see the following message:</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Welcome message</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch02-fig01.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>If you follow the instructions and click on the link, you will be prompted to select the language that will be used during the installation. It will also be the default language in which the WebIssues system will display all messages.</para>

      <para>In the next step of the installation, basic information about your server will be displayed: the name of the instance (usually <literal>default</literal>, unless you create multiple instances of the server within a single installation), the base URL of the server and the path of the directory in which the configuration file will be created. You will also see the version of PHP, the web server and the operating system, and the name of the computer on which you're installing WebIssues. After verifying this information, proceed to the next step.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Configuring the database connection</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch02-fig02.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>You will be asked to enter information necessary to connect to the database that you previously created. Select the type of the database, then enter the host name of the database server, if it's located on a different computer than the web server, the name of the database and the login and password of a user with the right to create tables in the database. In case of SQL Server, you can leave the user name and password blank to use integrated Windows authentication.</para>

      <para>Leave the <guilabel>Install a new server</guilabel> option selected if you are creating a new server. If you want to create a new configuration file for a previously created server instead, select the <guilabel>Use an existing server</guilabel> option. In that case, you will not be prompted for the parameters of the server and the database will not be modified, unless it needs to be updated to a newer version.</para>

      <note>
        <title>Note</title>
        <para>You can also specify a prefix which will be added before the names of all tables and other objects in the database. For example, if you choose <literal>wi_</literal> prefix, tables will be named <literal>wi_server</literal>, <literal>wi_users</literal>, etc.</para>
        <para>By choosing a unique prefix, you can install many different applications using a single database. You can also create several separate instances of the WebIssues server in a single database.</para>
      </note>

      <para>Enter the necessary information and proceed to the next step. The WebIssues system will try to connect to the database server, and in case of an error it will display an appropriate message. If the connection succeeds, you will see the following page:</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Parameters of the new server</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch02-fig03.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Enter the name of the server which will be visible to all users in the title bar. Also enter the password for the Administrator account, which you can later use to log into the server and change its settings.</para>

      <para>By default, the installer will create several predefined types of issues and views. You should leave this setting to quickly start working with the system. Later you will be able to freely adjust and even remove those built-in types. However, if you want to manually create all types of issues from scratch, select <guilabel>Do not install any issue types</guilabel>.</para>

      <para>Go to the next page, which contains a brief summary of the operations that will be performed. Click <guibutton>Install</guibutton> to begin the installation. This may take some time. If the installation is successful, a message will appear and you can start using the system.</para>

      <tip>
        <title>Tip</title>
        <para>In order to create a new configuration file in the future, for example after moving the database to another server, simply delete the configuration file. Then you will be prompted to run the installer which will let you create a new configuration file with appropriate settings.</para>
      </tip>

    </sect2>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="webissues.prep.setup">
    <title>Initial setup</title>

    <para>After installing the new WebIssues server, it contains initial configuration and settings, but before you can start using it, you have to do a few more things. First, you must create accounts for users that will use the system. Secondly, you need to create projects and folders in which the issues will be stored.</para>

    <sect2 id="webissues.prep.setup.users">
      <title>User accounts</title>

      <para>Let's start with creating user accounts. Click the <guilabel>Administration Panel</guilabel> link in the upper right corner of the window, then select <guilabel>User Accounts</guilabel>. You should see a single user named Administrator, which was created by the installer.</para>

      <para>Create your personal account, so you don't have to log in as Administrator. To do this, click <guilabel>Add user</guilabel>, then enter your name and the login and password that you will be using to log into the system. Then press <guibutton>OK</guibutton>.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Creating a user account</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch02-fig04.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Repeat the above steps to create accounts for other people who will use the system. For each of them you need to specify the initial password, but for greater security, you can select the <guilabel>User must change password at next logon</guilabel> option, if you want them to set their own password when logging into the system.</para>

      <para>In the WebIssues system there may be more users with administrator privileges. To change permissions of a user, select him by clicking his name in the list, then click <guilabel>Change Access</guilabel>. You can choose the System Administrator or Regular User permission, and also disable access to the system for given user. Press <guibutton>OK</guibutton> to confirm the changes.</para>

      <tip>
        <title>Tip</title>
        <para>The System Administrator has access to the Administration Panel, and is the administrator of all existing projects, even if he's not explicitly their member. Thus grant this permission only to persons that you trust.</para>
      </tip>

      <para>A configured list of user accounts may look like the figure below:</para>

      <figure>
        <title>List of user accounts</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch02-fig05.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>For more information on administering user accounts, read <xref linkend="webissues.admin.users"/>.</para>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="webissues.prep.setup.projects">
      <title>Projects and folders</title>

      <para>Click on the <guilabel>Web Client</guilabel> link in the upper right corner of the window to go to the main part of the WebIssues system. On the left you'll see an empty projects and folders tree. Click <guilabel>Manage Projects</guilabel> and then use the <guilabel>Add Project</guilabel> command to create the first project. Name it <quote>My first project</quote> and press <guibutton>OK</guibutton>.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Creating a project</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch02-fig06.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>The new project will appear in the tree. Click on this project to select it, and you will see a number of operations that you can perform on that project. Let's begin by creating folders. Click <guilabel>Add Folder</guilabel> and create a folder called <quote>Bugs</quote>, selecting the type of issues with the same name.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Creating a folder</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch02-fig07.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>After creating a folder, it will be displayed in the tree below the project. Select the project again and add another folder of type Tasks. Then repeat the same step to create a Forums folder. The projects tree will look like this:</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Projects tree</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch02-fig08.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>For now, the newly created project is only available to system administrators. To grant access to other users, select the project and click <guilabel>Project Members</guilabel>. You will see an empty list. Now click <guilabel>Add members</guilabel> and select all users except the Administrator account. Click <guibutton>OK</guibutton>.</para>

      <para>You can also assign an administrator right for the project to selected members. Select a user and click <guilabel>Change Access</guilabel>. Then select the access level in a similar way as in case of changing user's access to the system.</para>

      <tip>
        <title>Tip</title>
        <para>The Project Administrator can create and modify folders, modify the project description and change permissions of other users for this project. He can also delete issues and delete and modify other users' comments.</para>
      </tip>

      <para>A configured list of members of the project may look like below:</para>

      <figure>
        <title>List of project members</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch02-fig09.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Click <guibutton>OK</guibutton> to return to the main window. The project and folders will appear in the tree on the left side on the window. Also the global lists of issues for each of the issue types will appear in the tree.</para>

      <tip>
        <title>Tip</title>
        <para>If you use the Desktop Client, the commands for managing projects and folders are available directly in the main window of the program. Activate the projects tree by clicking on it to be able to access these commands (provided that you have appropriate permissions).</para>
      </tip>

      <para>Read <xref linkend="webissues.admin.projects"/> later in this book to learn more about administration of projects and folders.</para>

    </sect2>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="webissues.prep.notifications">
    <title>Sending emails</title>

    <para>The WebIssues system has the ability to send emails associated with alerts or subscriptions. This is optional, because the configuration of your computer or hosting service doesn't always allow this, and it's not needed in all cases. If you want to use alerts with email notifications or other features which require sending emails, you must perform two additional configuration steps.</para>

    <sect2 id="webissues.prep.nofitications.email">
      <title>Email settings</title>

      <para>First, go to the Administration Panel and click <guilabel>Email Settings</guilabel> to configure sending emails.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Email settings</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch02-fig10.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>If PHP on your server is configured so that it has the ability to send emails using the <literal>sendmail</literal> program or a local SMTP server, select <guilabel>Standard PHP mailer</guilabel> and enter the address from which the messages will be sent.</para>

      <note>
        <title>Note</title>
        <para>For more information on setting up the standard mechanism for sending emails which is built into PHP, please visit <ulink url="http://php.net/manual/en/mail.configuration.php"/>.</para>
      </note>

      <para>You can also send emails using an external SMTP server. You can either use your company or organization's mail server, or any public email service (e.g. gmail). Select <guilabel>Custom SMTP server</guilabel> and enter the address of the sender. In the <guilabel>SMTP Server</guilabel> section, type the address of the server and the port number of the email service (usually 25 or 587 for encrypted connections). Select the encryption mode, if the SMTP server supports encrypted communication. Also enter the user name and password required to access the SMTP server.</para>

      <para>Click <guibutton>Test Connection</guibutton> to check whether the SMTP configuration is correct. The WebIssues system will send a test message to its own address. If you receive it, it means that the configuration is correct. Don't forget to save the configuration by clicking <guibutton>OK</guibutton>.</para>

      <para>Since emails are sent in HTML format, it is possible to include hyperlinks to the folder related to the notification, as well as to individual issues. To enable hyperlinks, you need to enter the base URL at which the WebIssues server is installed. The URL should include the protocol and the trailing slash, for instance <literal>http://www.example.com/</literal>. Click <guibutton>Detect</guibutton> to automatically enter the address of the current page. Note that the URL should contain the fully qualified domain name of the server to make it available to all users. If the URL is left blank, emails will be sent without links.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Hyperlinks</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch02-fig10-01.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="webissues.prep.nofitications.cron">
      <title>Cron jobs</title>

      <para>The second step is to set up a recurring task which will send the notifications. This task should be executed at least once an hour, but in order to receive immediate notification more quickly, it's recommended that this task is performed at intervals of 5 to 15 minutes.</para>

      <para>In case of Unix/Linux, you can use the <literal>cron</literal> jobs mechanism. To add a cron job, modify <filename>/etc/crontab</filename> or use a graphical tool for managing jobs. If you use Windows, open the Task Scheduler and create a new task. For more information, please visit <ulink url="http://wiki.mimec.org/wiki/WebIssues/Installation"/>.</para>

      <note>
        <title>Note</title>
        <para>Some hosting services provide the ability to define recurring tasks via shell access, or by their administration panel. Refer to the documentation of your service for more information.</para>
        <para>If your hosting service does not offer the ability to run periodic tasks, you can install such task on another computer. For example, you can use one of the available online cron services &mdash; some of them are available for free.</para>
      </note>

      <para>If the job is executed locally, it should run the <literal>cron/job.php</literal> script using the PHP interpreter. For more information about running PHP from the command line, see <ulink url="http://www.php.net/manual/en/features.commandline.options.php"/>.</para>

      <para>If you use an external cron service or run the task from another computer, the script should be run remotely through its full URL, for example <literal>http://www.example.com/cron/job.php</literal>. To do this, you can for example use a program like <literal>wget</literal> or <literal>curl</literal>.</para>

      <para>To check whether the cron job is being executed, go to the Administration Panel and click <guilabel>General Information</guilabel>. In the <guilabel>Server Configuration</guilabel> section, the time when the job was last run is displayed. Each execution of the job is also logged in the Event Log of the WebIssues system.</para>

      <tip>
        <title>Tip</title>
        <para>Configuring email settings and cron job doesn't mean that any notifications are actually sent. In order to configure email notifications, you must create alerts for selected folders or global lists and set the appropriate email type. Also make sure that a valid email address is entered in your user preferences. For more information about using email notifications please refer to <xref linkend="webissues.track.alerts" />.</para>
      </tip>

    </sect2>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="webissues.prep.inbox">
    <title>Email inbox</title>

    <para>The WebIssues system also has the ability to receive emails from selected email account and create issues based on these emails, as well as create comments and attachments for existing issues. Combined with email subscriptions, this allows for setting up two way email communication with the WebIssues system. It's even possible for external users, who don't have a WebIssues account, to communicate with the WebIssues system in this way, which is very useful for various support services.</para>

    <para>Although it is possible to use email inbox without sending emails, in that case you won't be able to use automatic replies and subscriptions. Also when sending emails is not configured, WebIssues users don't have an associated email account, so all emails are treated as if they are sent by external users. For more information about configuring the outbound email server, see <xref linkend="webissues.prep.nofitications.email" />. You also must ensure that the cron job is correctly configured. For more information, see <xref linkend="webissues.prep.nofitications.cron" />.</para>

    <sect2 id="webissues.prep.inbox.settings">
      <title>Inbox settings</title>

      <para>If you want the WebIssues system to receive emails, go to the Administration Panel and click <guilabel>Inbox Settings</guilabel>.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Inbox settings</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch02-fig11.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Select the protocol that will be used to communicate with the email server. It is recommended to use an <guilabel>IMAP server</guilabel> if possible, however a <guilabel>POP3 server</guilabel> is also supported. Also specify the email address of the inbox. In the <guilabel>Inbox Server</guilabel> section, enter the address of the server and the port number. Select the appropriate encryption mode if your server supports it. Also specify the user name and password used to authenticate the connection. You can specify the name of the mailbox from which messages will be processed. If you leave it empty, the current user's personal inbox will be assumed.</para>

      <note>
        <title>Note</title>
        <para>Although the same email address can be used for sending outgoing messages and for the email inbox, it is recommended to use two separate email addresses. This reduces the risk of creating an infinite loop when a notification email is bounced by the recipient's email server, and the bounced message is processed by the email inbox.</para>
      </note>

      <para>Enable the <guilabel>Do not validate server certificate</guilabel> option if you are using an encrypted connection to a local server which uses a self-signed certificate. When using an IMAP server, you can also enable the <guilabel>Leave processed messages on the server</guilabel>. By default, WebIssues will automatically delete processed emails from the server. If you enable this option, messages will be only marked as read and they will be left on the server. In that case you need to ensure that there is some retention policy on the server which removes old emails to prevent filling the inbox. Note that this option is not available when using a POP3 server.</para>

      <para>Click <guibutton>Test Connection</guibutton> to confirm that the WebIssues can connect to the server using the specified information. It will not process any messages, only a success or error message will be displayed.</para>

      <para>When an email is sent to the WebIssues server inbox, it is registered as a new issue in the selected folder. The subject of the message becomes the name of the issue. All attributes are set to their initial, default values. The text body of the email is automatically added as the description of the issue, along with most important message headers, including the sender and recipients. When the email has a HTML body, it is added as an attachment, which can be easily opened and viewed in the browser. Any files attached to the email are also added as attachments to the issue.</para>

      <para>When the subject of the email contains an identifier enclosed in square brackets, for example <literal>[#123]</literal>, the body of the email is added as a new comment to the issue with given identifier. The HTML body and attached files are added as attachments to the issue. Typically you can add comments to existing issues by simply responding to the confirmation message sent when the issue is created or to the subscription notification message, because they already contain the identifier of the issue in the subject. Note that you should include your comment at the beginning of the email. The body of the quoted notification message will not be included in the comment, because it is automatically cut off at the first line containing the dashes.</para>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="webissues.prep.inbox.external">
      <title>External users</title>

      <para>By default only messages sent by WebIssues users are accepted. The sender's email address is compared with the email address configured in the user's preferences. Emails sent from addresses which do not match any WebIssues users are ignored. Note that the issue is created or modified on behalf of the user associated with the email address, so that user must have access to the project and folder containing the issue. Otherwise the message is ignored and a warning is added to the Event Log.</para>

      <para>If you enable the <guilabel>Accept messages from external users</guilabel> option, messages sent from addresses which don't have a matching WebIssues user will also be accepted. In that case you must also select the <guilabel>Robot user account</guilabel> on whose behalf such issues will be created or modified. The robot user account also must have access to the project containing the issue, unless it is a public project. By changing the permissions of the robot user account, you can control which parts of the system are accessible to external users. Although the issue appears to be created or modified by the robot user, the actual sender of the message can be seen in the headers in the beginning of the description or comment.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>External users</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch02-fig12.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <tip>
        <title>Tip</title>
        <para>When messages from external users are accepted, the WebIssues server will not attempt to filter the received messages in any way. If you want to blacklist or whitelist certain addresses or filter out spam and other unwanted messages, you should configure such filtering on the email server.</para>
        <para>For example, you can create a separate mailbox from which WebIssues receives messages, and set up a rule which only moves messages matching certain criteria to this mailbox. Refer to the documentation of your email server for more information.</para>
      </tip>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="webissues.prep.inbox.mapping">
      <title>Folder mapping</title>

      <para>In the simplest scenario, all issues are created in a single folder, which can be selected using the <guilabel>Default folder</guilabel> option. However, you can also enable the <guilabel>Map address extensions to project and folder</guilabel> option, which makes it possible to determine the project and folder where the issue is created based on the address used to send the message to the WebIssues inbox.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Folder mapping</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch02-fig13.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>There are two ways to set up mapping the email address to project and folder. The first way is to enable email address extensions in the email server. For example, when the inbox address is <literal>service@example.com</literal>, an email sent to <literal>service+myproject-bugs@example.com</literal> will be registered as an issue in the <quote>My project</quote> project, in the <quote>Bugs</quote> folder. Another solution is to set up an alias, for example <literal>service-myproject-bugs@example.com</literal>, which maps to the <literal>service@example.com</literal> address. Refer to the email server's documentation for more information about setting up address extensions and aliases.</para>

      <note>
        <title>Note</title>
        <para>In order for the folder mapping to work, the email address must contain the account name, as defined in the inbox email address, followed by a <literal>+</literal> or <literal>-</literal> character, part of the project name, a <literal>-</literal> and part of the folder name. The domain part must match the inbox email address. The address must be explicitly specified in either To or CC field of the email. Spaces and other non-alphanumeric characters in project and folder names are ignored. Only a part of the project or folder name must match, but the mapping must be unambiguous.</para>
        <para>For example, when a project is named <quote>My first project</quote>, both <literal>service+first-bugs@example.com</literal> and <literal>service+firstproject-bugs@example.com</literal> will match. However, if there are more projects containing <quote>first</quote> in their name, the former example will not be successfully mapped, because it's ambiguous.</para>
        <para>Be careful when using accented or non-Latin characters in project and folder names, because not all email servers will accept email addresses containing such characters. In such case you can add Latin-only words to project and folder names which can be used for mapping email addresses.</para>
      </note>

      <para>When the folder cannot be automatically determined from the email address, the issue is created in the selected default folder. However, when folder mapping is enabled, it is possible not to specify a default folder. In that case any email which cannot be successfully mapped will be ignored and a warning will be added to the Event Log. Also note that the actual user or the robot user must have access to the folder, whether it's a mapped folder or the default one.</para>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="webissues.prep.inbox.sending">
      <title>Responses and subscriptions</title>

      <para>When the <guilabel>Send responses when issues are created</guilabel> option is enabled, a confirmation message is sent back to the sender when a new issue is created through the inbox. The automatic reply contains the identifier and the name of the issue. By responding to this message, additional comments and attachments can be created, for example in order to provide more information or ask about the status of the issue.</para>

      <para>When the <guilabel>Subscribe senders to created issues</guilabel> option is enabled, the sender of the message is automatically subscribed to the issue created through the inbox. In that case any changes made by other users, including editing attributes, modifying the description, adding comments and attachments, are automatically sent as notification emails. See <xref linkend="webissues.track.subscriptions" /> for more information.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Sending emails</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch02-fig14.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>By responding to the subscription notification message, when the email inbox is enabled, it is possible to add more comments and attachments to the issue. This way you can track the state of issues and add comments to it entirely by email, without having to log into the WebIssues system.</para>

      <para>Automatic subscriptions also work for external users. This makes it possible for persons without a WebIssues account to receive notifications and interact with issues that they created. In a typical service desk scenario, when someone sends a message to the inbox account, an issue is created and the sender is automatically subscribed to the issue. When a support person modifies the issue or adds a comment using the WebIssues system, a subscription notification is automatically sent to the creator of the issue. He can then reply to the notification email in order to provide more information. This way external users can communicate with the WebIssues system using email and entire communication is tracked in the issue history.</para>

      <para>You can also enable anonymous access to allow external users to see all issues from public projects using the Web Client, without having to log in. However, keep in mind that in that case all users will have access to all issues, not only those created by themselves. For more information about enabling anonymous access, see <xref linkend="webissues.custom.access"/>.</para>

      <para>Note that the sender is not subscribed to an existing issue when adding a comment. Also an automatic response is not sent in that case. Any other recipients of the email are not automatically subscribed to the created issue.</para>

    </sect2>

  </sect1>

</chapter>
