<chapter id="webissues.work">
  <title>Working with issues</title>

  <para>This chapter describes the most important functions of the WebIssues system, such as creating and editing issues and searching for information. It should be read by all users of the system.</para>

  <sect1 id="webissues.work.clients">
    <title>Client applications</title>

    <para>The WebIssues system can be accessed by the WebIssues Web Client, available through a web browser, as well as a dedicated client application &mdash; the WebIssues Desktop Client. You can choose a solution that fits your needs better.</para>

    <para>The main advantage of the Web Client is that you can use the WebIssues system on any computer (or even a mobile device), anywhere in the world, if the system is available via the Internet. You can use any web browser and you don't need to install any additional software.</para>

    <para>The advantage of the Desktop Client is above all that it's much faster and more convenient than the web interface. Searching and filtering works in real time and the program continually updates the statistics for all configured alerts. So it's the best option for those who use the WebIssues system a lot.</para>

    <para>This diversity is similar to the use of electronic mail. Some people use email programs installed on their computer, others prefer to use email via a web browser.</para>

    <para>Actually there are more similarities, because the main window of the application consists of three panels resembling popular email programs. On the left there is a tree of projects and folders. On the right at the top there is a list of issues in the selected folder. On the right at the bottom there are the details of the selected issue. The selected folder and issue are highlighted, and you can perform various operations with them.</para>

    <para>Below is the Web Client window showing a few issues and the history of an issue:</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Web Client application</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch03-fig01.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Below is the Desktop Client window displaying the same information:</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Desktop Client application</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch03-fig02.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>As you can see on these figures, the user interface of both client applications is very similar. The key differences between them are listed below:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Commands in the Desktop Client are available through a single toolbar, which varies depending on which panel is currently active. You can also use the contextual menus (available by clicking the right mouse button on the selected item) and keyboard shortcuts. On the other hand, in the Web Client commands are available separately within each of the panels.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>In the Desktop Client, the whole list of issues and the entire history of the selected issue is available. You can scroll through the contents of individual panels using sliders. The Web Client displays only a limited number of issues and items in the history, so you must navigate between pages to see further issues and history.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>The Desktop Client automatically refreshes the lists and details of issues, so you can almost immediately see changes made ​​by others. In the Web Client you have to manually refresh the page to see updated information.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>In the Desktop Client you can open separate windows containing lists of issues and issue details. Just double-click on the folder or issue. This way you can view the contents of multiple folders, or the history of several issues side by side. On the other hand, most browsers give you the ability to open links in a new window or tab, so you can obtain a similar effect in the Web Client.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>To make it easier to work with the system, both the names of the functions and the graphic symbols of various objects are the same in both client applications. Below is a list of most important graphic symbols used in the WebIssues system:</para>
     
    <figure>
      <title>Graphic symbols</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch03-fig03.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <tip>
      <title>Tip</title>
      <para>Both applications provide access to commonly used administrative functions, such as managing projects, users and types of issues. However, some administrative functions are only available through the web browser. These include system configuration and the event log.</para>
    </tip>

    <para>The Desktop Client can be installed on any computer with Windows (XP or later versions), Linux or Mac OS X. Installation packages exist for these systems. You can also compile and install the application from source &mdash; for more information, refer to the <literal>INSTALL</literal> file attached in the source package.</para>

    <para>There is also a WebIssues Portable Client application which you can run from any portable device (e.g. a USB flash drive) or media (e.g. a compact disk) without installing on your computer. It can be used together with the <ulink url="http://portableapps.com">PortableApps.com</ulink> platform or stand alone. Except for this, it is completely the same as the Desktop Client.</para>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="webissues.work.login">
    <title>Logging into the system</title>

    <para>To log into the system using a web browser, simply type the URL of the WebIssues server in the address bar, for example <literal>http://www.example.com</literal>, and press <shortcut><keycap>ENTER</keycap></shortcut>. You can add the address of the server as a bookmark in your browser to avoid having to type it each time.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Logging into the Web Client</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch03-fig04.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>In the login window, type your username and password. If they are correct, you will be redirected to the main window. You may also be asked to enter a new password, if the password was set by the administrator of the system and he forced you to change it. Depending on its settings, your browser may offer to remember passwords.</para>

    <para>To log in through the Desktop Client, run it and enter the URL of the server in the address bar, and then press <shortcut><keycap>ENTER</keycap></shortcut>. When the login window appears, enter your username and password. As with the Web Client, you may be asked to change your password.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Logging into the Desktop Client</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch03-fig05.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The Desktop Client automatically remembers the addresses of all WebIssues servers it connects to. You can select a server from the list and double-click to connect to it. You can also choose to remember the password to avoid having to enter it each time. If you want to log in as another user, select a server from the list, right click and select <guilabel>Connect as</guilabel>. The program remembers the previously used logins for each server and displays them in the contextual menu.</para>

    <para>After logging into the WebIssues system, you can change your password at any time. In the Web Client, click <guilabel>Tools</guilabel> in the upper right corner of the window, and then click <guilabel>Change Password</guilabel>. In the Desktop Client, this command is always available in the main window's toolbar. Enter your old password, and then enter the new password twice and click <guibutton>OK</guibutton>.</para>

    <note>
      <title>Note</title>
      <para>If the WebIssues server is properly configured, you can connect to it using an encrypted HTTPS connection. To do this, type the address in the browser or the Desktop Client, for example <literal>https://www.example.com</literal>. If the server certificate is invalid, a warning will be displayed. The information that the connection is encrypted is displayed in the lower right corner of the Desktop Client's window, and in the browser it's usually displayed next to the address bar.</para>
      <para>On Windows and OS X the Desktop Client automatically detects system proxy settings. However in case of Linux, you must enter the connection parameters if you want to use a proxy. For more information, see <xref linkend="webissues.work.personal.client"/>.</para>
    </note>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="webissues.work.issues">
    <title>Creating and editing issues</title>

    <para>Click on the folder named Bugs to open it. If you have just created a new server, the folder will be empty, so let's start with creating the first issue.</para>

    <sect2 id="webissues.work.issues.attributes">
      <title>Attributes of an issue</title>

      <para>Select the <guilabel>Add issue</guilabel> command (if you are using the Desktop Client, you must click on the list of issues for the command to appear). The following window will be displayed:</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Adding an issue</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch03-fig06.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>The name of the issue is a required field, so let's type <quote>My first issue</quote>. The remaining fields are the attributes of the issue. Status and Priority are also required fields, but they have a default initial value. Depending on the type of the attributes, they accept different kinds of values:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Text</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>It's the simplest attribute that can have any value. It may have a specified minimum and maximum length. It may also be a single line of text or a field where you can enter multiple lines of text. An example of a text attribute is the Version field.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Dropdown list</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>This attribute accepts one of the specific values​​, just like the Status field, where you have to choose one of Active, Resolved or Closed. There is also a variant of this attribute that accepts any value, and the list is merely auxiliary, and another variant where you can enter mutliple values separated with commas.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>User</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>The value of this attribute can be the name of any user of the WebIssues system or a member of the project. The Assigned To field is an example of such attribute. There is also a variant where you can select mutliple users separated with commas.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Numeric</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>The value of this attribute can be an integer or a decimal value with specified number of decimal places. It may have a specified minimum and maximum value. An example of a numeric attribute is Severity, which may be in the range from 1 (most critical bug) to 3 (insignificant bug).</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Date</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>The value of this attribute can be any valid date that can be entered manually or selected using a drop down calendar. An example is the Due Date attribute of the Tasks issue type. There is also a version accepting both date and time.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <para>For starters, assign the bug to yourself and change its severity to 1 &mdash; after all, it's the first bug recorded in the system.</para>

      <tip>
        <title>Tip</title>
        <para>If you don't see some user in the drop down list, it probably means that the user was not added to the project members; see <xref linkend="webissues.admin.users"/>.</para>
      </tip>

      <para>Then press <guibutton>OK</guibutton>. If the value of one of the attributes is incorrect, you will receive an error. Otherwise, the new issue will appear in the list and its details will be displayed below:</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Details of the new issue</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch03-fig07.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="webissues.work.issues.comments">
      <title>Comments and editing</title>

      <para>For now, it doen't look very impressive. The system has registered that you have created the issue, you gave it the name and changed the value of two attributes. Now let's write a comment. To do this, choose <guilabel>Add Comment</guilabel> (make sure that the history of the issue is the active panel, if you are using the Desktop Client).</para>

      <para>The new window consists almost entirely of a text edit box. In case of the Desktop Client, you can leave this window open and return to another window, for example, to view the history of the issue. Using a web browser you can also add a new comment in a separate window, if you right-click on the link and select an appropriate option.</para>

      <para>Returning to our window, type the text of the comment regarding the first issue:</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Adding a comment</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch03-fig08.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>The text will appear exactly as typed, with all spaces and new lines preserved. This allows you, for example, to paste fragments of code and error logs without worrying that they will become unreadable. Long lines are automatically wrapped, depending on the width of the window. Web addresses and email addresses are automatically converted into clickable links.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Issue history with a comment</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch03-fig09.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <tip>
        <title>Tip</title>
        <para>Automatic recognition of links works not only in the text of comments, but also in the names of issues and attribute values​​, and even in descriptions of attachments.</para>
      </tip>

      <para>You can also create links to other issues and to comments or attachments. To demonstrate this, let's create another issue called <quote>Second issue</quote>, leaving the default values ​​of attributes. Let's assume that the identifier of the first issue is #1, and the second is #5.</para>

      <para>If you add a comment to the first issue, and type <quote>#5</quote>, it will be replaced with a link to the other issue. Similarly, if you now add a comment to the second issue, writing <quote>#1</quote>, it will become a link to the first issue. In this way, you can create links between issues, refer to other comments in your own comments, etc.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Link to an issue</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch03-fig10.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <note>
        <title>Note</title>
        <para>Identifiers of issues are unique and increasing, but not necessarily in consecutive numerical order. In our example, the ID of the second issue is #5, not #2, because the identifiers are also assigned to comments, attachments and other changes, making them easier to manage by the system.</para>
      </note>

      <para>To quickly go to the issue, comment or attachment with the given identifier, you can also use the Go To Item command. In the Web Client, click <guilabel>Tools</guilabel> in the the upper right corner of the window, then click <guilabel>Go To Item</guilabel>. In the Desktop Client this command is always available in the the main window toolbar, you can also press <shortcut><keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>G</keycap></keycombo></shortcut>.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Going to an item</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch03-fig11.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Then enter the identifier you are looking for and press <guibutton>OK</guibutton>. If there is an issue with this identifier, it will be displayed. If the identifier represents a comment or an attachment, you will see the issue which contains the item, and the history will be scrolled to the item.</para>

      <para>The <guilabel>Edit Attributes</guilabel> command allows you to edit issue, i.e., change the value of each attribute and the name of the issue. Select the first issue and select that command. You will see the same window as in case of adding a new issue, containing current values ​​of attributes. Change the status of issue to Resolved, and select Fixed in the Resolution field. Then press <guibutton>OK</guibutton> to save your changes.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Changing attributes of an issue</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch03-fig12.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Note that the WebIssues system automatically remembers your changes and displays them in the history of the issue. This allows you to track the entire life cycle of the issue, changes of its status and all operations performed with the issue.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Issue history after the change</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch03-fig13.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>By default the issue history contains all changes, comments and attachments. If you don't want to see the full history of the issue, but for example only comments, select one of the filtering options available in the upper right corner of the history view. To search for a specific text in a comment or another change, in the Desktop Client you can use the <guilabel>Search</guilabel> command or press <shortcut><keycombo><keycap>Ctrl</keycap><keycap>F</keycap></keycombo></shortcut> to display the search bar. Enter the text you want to search and then use the <shortcut><keycap>F3</keycap></shortcut> and <shortcut><keycombo><keycap>Shift</keycap><keycap>F3</keycap></keycombo ></shortcut> keys to find the next or previous occurrence of text in the history of the issue. In the Web Client you can use the search function of the browser.</para>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="webissues.work.issues.attach">
      <title>Adding attachments</title>

      <para>You already know how to add a comment to describe the issue or discuss it. However it's better to add long passages of text (such as error logs) as separate attachments. This way you can also attach image files, documents and other types of files to the issue, just like attachments to email messages.</para>

      <para>To attach a file, select <guilabel>Add Attachment</guilabel>. Then select the file you want to add, and optionally enter a brief description of the attachment.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Adding an attachment</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch03-fig14.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>The new attachment is visible in the history of the issue:</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Issue history with an attachment</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch03-fig15.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Click the link to open the attached file or to save it to disk. The Desktop Client by default always asks if you want to open or save the file. You can also right-click to select the appropriate option from the context menu. By changing the program settings you can select the default action for attachments, and change the maximum amount of disk space used to store temporary files.</para>

      <para>In case of the Web Client, depending on the file type and the configuration of your browser, clicking on a link will open the attachment or save it to the disk. Images and text files will generally be opened directly in the browser. In most browsers you can also click the right mouse button above the link to choose an action from the context menu.</para>

      <note>
        <title>Note</title>
        <para>The maximum size of files which can be attached to an issue depends on the configuration of the WebIssues system. You can change it in the WebIssues system settings (see <xref linkend="webissues.custom.settings"/> for more information). Uploading large attachments also requires appropriate configuration of the web server and PHP. For more information, please visit <ulink url="http://php.net/manual/en/features.file-upload.common-pitfalls.php"/>.</para>
        <para>By default, small attachments are stored in the database, and large files are stored directly in the file system. Depending on your needs, you can change the threshold value or force storing all attachments only in the database or the file system, by changing WebIssues system settings. For client applications it doesn't matter how the attachments are stored.</para>
      </note>

    </sect2>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="webissues.work.views">
    <title>Filtering issues</title>

    <para>Over time, folders contain more and more issues and finding the desired information can become difficult. You can of course sort the list of issues using any column, not only by identifiers, but also by name or the value of any attribute. This can help you find the information you need, but it's not always enough.</para>

    <para>The list of issues also has a quick search function. Enter a word or its fragment in the text box on the right side above the list and press <guibutton>Search</guibutton>, and you will see only issues which contain the text in their name. In the Desktop Client the search is performed immediately as you type, you can also press <shortcut><keycap>F3</keycap></shortcut> to quickly activate the search box. You can also search by the name of the user who created or modified the issue, as well as by any Text, Dropdown list or User attribute. To select the column in which you want to search, click the icon to the left of the search box and select the appropriate option. After entering the text you want to search, only the issues containing this text in the selected column will be displayed.</para>

    <tip>
      <title>Tip</title>
      <para>To quickly find a issue with given identifier, use the <guilabel>Go To item</guilabel> command. See <xref linkend="webissues.work.issues.comments"/> for more information about identifiers of issues, comments and attachments.</para>
    </tip>

    <para>In everyday work, however, it's most useful to use views. Each view has filter conditions, which limit the displayed list of issues to those that meet certain criteria. Each view also has its own column layout, and default sort order. In other words, the view defines which issues from all issues in the folder are visible, and which columns from all available columns are displayed.</para>

    <para>What views are available depends on the type of issues in the folder. The only exception is the <quote>All Issues</quote> view, which exists for each issue type and has no filter conditions, and therefore (as the name implies) displays all the issues in the current folder.</para>

    <para>Open the Bugs folder, and then expand the list of views on the left side above the list of issues. You'll see the default <quote>All Issues</quote> view, and a few public views:</para>

    <figure>
      <title>View selection</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch03-fig16.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Select the <quote>Active Bugs</quote> view from the list. Note that now the list of issues contains only the second issue, since you have just changed the status of the first issue to Resolved.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>List of active bugs</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch03-fig17.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Select other available views, to see that every time different issues are displayed and the layout of visible columns changes. This allows each user to focus only on those issues that are currently interesting &mdash; for example, a tester can view the list of fixed bugs, that need to be verified, and a developer can display the list of bugs assigned to him, that must be solved.</para>

    <tip>
      <title>Tip</title>
      <para>Although views make it much easier to work with a large number of issues, you should anticipate what will happen in your system over the next few years. For example, if there are 10 new issues created every day by average, in a year there will be more than 3000 issues.</para>
      <para>Although there is no specified limit of issues per one folder, a large number of issues  may adversely affect system performance. In this situation, you should divide the issues into separate folders, for example, by date of creation or a version of the project to which they refer.</para>
    </tip>

    <para>Sometimes it is not enough to use the existing public views. In that case, you can create your own, personal views, which may have any filtering criteria, columns and sorting order.</para>

    <para>Click <guilabel>Add View</guilabel> to quickly create a new view for the current type of issues. Suppose you want to display only critical bugs, so we will call our view <quote>Critical bugs</quote>. The Severity column is not needed, because it will always have a value of 1, so uncheck it on the list of columns. Add the Created By and Created Date columns, so that you know who and when created the the issue. To move the Assigned To and Status columns to the end of the list, set the values defining their order to 10 and 11, respectively.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Editing view columns</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch03-fig18.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Click the <guibutton>Update</guibutton> button to see how the new column layout of the view will look. Leave the default sort order to display issues from oldest to newest. Then proceed to editing the filters. Enable the filter for the Severity column and type 1 as the parameter of the condition:</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Editing the filter</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch03-fig19.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Save your changes by clicking <guibutton>OK</guibutton>. The Views drop-down list now includes a personal view named <quote>Critical bugs</quote>. After selecting it, the list of issues will only contain the first the issue, according to the selected filter criteria.</para>

    <para>Different filtering operators are available depending on the type of the column. For all types the <quote>is equal to</quote> and <quote>is not equal to</quote> operators are available. These operators can also compare the value of the column with the blank value. For text columns, drop-down lists, and user names, you can also search for a fragment of text using operators <quote>begins with</quote>, <quote>contains</quote> and <quote>ends with</quote>. You can also create criteria that can be fulfilled by a number of different values​​, using the <quote>in list</quote> operator and entering the individual values ​​separated by commas. In case of numbers and dates, you can use comparison operators &mdash; <quote>is less than</quote>, <quote>is less than or equal to</quote>, etc.</para>

    <para>Now suppose that we are only interested in these critical issues, which are active and in addition older than 7 days. Such view would be very useful for people supervising the process of resolving bugs. Click <guilabel>Edit View</guilabel> to edit the active view (first make sure that it's selected).</para>

    <para>Select two additional conditions for the Created Date and Status columns. In the first condition, select the <quote>is less than</quote> operator, and using the drop-down calendar, select Today. Then change the value of the parameter to <quote>[Today]-7</quote>. This value will be replaced by the current date minus 7 days, so only issues created more than 7 days ago will satisfy this condition. Also set the filter parameter for the Status field to Active.</para>

    <tip>
      <title>Tip</title>
      <para>Two special values can be used in the definition of a filter. The value <quote>[Today]</quote> is replaced by the current date (with the possibility of adding or subtracting a specified numer of days), an the value <quote>[Me]</quote> is replaced by the name of the current user.</para>
    </tip>

    <figure>
      <title>Changing the filter</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch03-fig20.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Click <guibutton>Update</guibutton> to see all the filters. Note that you can add new conditions containing those fields that are already used. Thanks to this you can create complex filters, such as <quote>older than seven days but not older than a month</quote>.</para>

    <para>Save your changes by clicking <guibutton>OK</guibutton>. Of course the list of issues will now be empty, since at this time there are no issues older than 7 days in the system.</para>

    <para>You can also create a new view based on an existing one. To do this, select the view you want to clone and use the <guilabel>Clone View</guilabel> command. By default the column settings and filtering criteria of the cloned view will be displayed. Customize them according to your needs and click <guibutton>OK</guibutton> to create a new view. This way you can also create personal views based on existing public views.</para>

    <para>You can create any number of personal views. They won't be visible to any other user. However they will be available for each folder that contains issues of the same type. To create, modify, rename, and delete your views, open the folder of the given type, and click <guilabel>Manage Views</guilabel>. A new window will be opened containing a list of all your views with detailed information.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Managing views</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch03-fig21.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>If you are a system administrator, you can also publish your views, so that they become accessible to all users, and manage public views for different types of issues. For more information, please read <xref linkend="webissues.custom.views"/>.</para>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="webissues.work.advanced">
    <title>Advanced editing</title>

    <para>It's possible to edit and remove comments in the WebIssues system. This can be done by the user who created the comment, and the administrator of the system or the project, to which the issue belongs. An administrator may thus act as a moderator of comments. Users without administrator privileges can't modify or delete comments created by other users.</para>

    <para>You can also change the name and description of the attachments, and to remove them. As with comments, this can be done by the user who created the attachment or by an administrator. You can't modify or replace the attached file &mdash; in order to do this, you need to remove the attachment and add the new file as a separate attachment.</para>

    <para>To edit or delete a comment or an attachment, click the <guilabel>Edit</guilabel> or <guilabel>Delete</guilabel> button in the upper right corner of each item in the issue history. If the comment or attachment has been edited, its last modification date and the person who edited it is displayed in addition to the creation date and author.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>History after editing a comment</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch03-fig22.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Only system administrator or project administrator may delete an existing issue, using the <guilabel>Delete Issue</guilabel> command.</para>

    <warning>
      <title>Warning</title>
      <para>Deleting an issue is irreversible and causes its entire history to be lost, so you should only do it in special circumstances.</para>
    </warning>

    <para>The administrator can also move an issue to another folder using the <guilabel>Move Issue</guilabel> command. The target folder must be of the same type as the issue being moved, because issues of various types can't be combined in a single folder. To move the issue to a folder belonging to another project, you must be an administrator of both projects, or the system administrator. The transfer operation is registered in the history of the issue.</para>

    <para>Each user can clone an existing issue, creating a new issue in the same folder, or another folder of the same type. To clone the issue, select the <guilabel>Clone Issue</guilabel> command, then select the destination folder and click <guibutton>OK</guibutton>. The new issue by default has the same name and attribute values​​, as the issue being cloned. If necessary, you can change these values, and then click <guibutton>OK</guibutton>. The new issue is in no way connected with the original issue, but you can create such connection using a link to the issue (see <xref linkend="webissues.work.issues.comments"/>). Also the history of changes won't be retained, and the comments and attachments won't be added to the cloned issue.</para>

    <para>There are also no restrictions when it comes to editing the attributes of the issue. Each user can freely modify them, but all changes are permanently recorded by the system and the only way of undoing them is to edit them once again.</para>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="webissues.work.export">
    <title>Printing and exporting</title>

    <para>The Desktop Client allows you to create simple reports containing a list of issues or details of the selected issue. These reports can be directly printed or saved as a PDF or HTML document. You can also export the list of issues to a CSV file, which can be imported into a spreadsheet or an external database.</para>

    <para>To create a report based on a list issues, open the folder, and select the view if you want to filter the issues. Make sure that the list of issues is active by clicking on it, and then select the <guibutton>Print</guibutton> command to print the report, or <guibutton>Export</guibutton> to save it in PDF format. To export the list as a document in HTML format or as a CSV file, expand the menu next to the <guibutton>Export</guibutton> button and select the appropriate option.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Printing a list of issues</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch03-fig23.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The report can be a simple table, which can contain only columns which are visible in the selected view, or all system columns and user-defined columns (attributes). The report may also have the form of a summary, including the properties and attributes of individual issues. When exporting to CSV format it is only possible create a table report.</para>

    <para>If you are saving the report to a file, select the type of the report, press <guibutton>OK</guibutton> and then select the folder where you want to save the file and enter its name. When printing a report, press <guibutton>OK</guibutton> and then select the printer and possibly other printing options. You can also press the <guibutton>Print Preview</guibutton> button to see the report before printing.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Print preview</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch03-fig24.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>You can zoom the preview in and out and move between pages. The preview window also lets you change the page orientation and other page settings, such as paper size or margins. Press the <guibutton>Print</guibutton> button to print the report.</para>

    <tip>
      <title>Tip</title>
      <para>Depending on the regional settings, Excel can sometimes incorrectly read the CSV file, so that all fields are displayed in one column, or misinterpret the character encoding. In this case, use the function of importing a text file, select the UTF-8 encoding and choose comma as the column separator. The same applies to other applications which import CSV files.</para>
    </tip>

    <para>To create a report based on a single issue, select the issue and make sure that the issue history view is active by clicking on it. Then select the <guibutton>Print</guibutton> command to print the report, or <guibutton>Export</guibutton> to save it in PDF format. You can also export the report as an HTML document by selecting the appropriate option from the dropdown menu.</para>

    <para>The report can be a summary that displays only the properties and attributes of the selected issue. It can also be a full report, containing the entire history of the issue. In case of a  full report, the filter chosen in the issue history view is taken into account (for example, only comments or only attachments).</para>

    <para>Similarly to the list of issues, if you are saving the report as a file, select the type of report, press <guibutton>OK</guibutton> and then select the folder where you want to save the file and enter its name. When printing the report, press <guibutton>OK</guibutton> and then select printing options. Before printing, you can also see the <guibutton>Print Preview</guibutton>.</para>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="webissues.work.personal">
    <title>Personalization</title>

    <para>Individual users of the WebIssues system can customize the regional settings &mdash; the language, time zone and format or numbers, date and time. Users of the Web Client can change the preferred number of issues displayed on a page of the list of issues and the number of elements on a page of the issue history. In the Desktop Client, you can change the user interface settings, fonts, intervals of updates, etc.</para>

    <tip>
      <title>Tip</title>
      <para>For more information about changing the default WebIssues system settings for all users, as well as other possibilities of customizing and configuring the system by the administrator, see <xref linkend="webissues.custom"/>.</para>
    </tip>

    <sect2 id="webissues.work.personal.prefs">
      <title>User preferences</title>

      <para>To change the user preferences in the Web Client, click <guilabel>Tools</guilabel> and then <guilabel>User Preferences</guilabel>. In the Desktop Client, the <guilabel>User Preferences</guilabel> command is available directly from the main window's toolbar.</para>

      <para>The <guilabel>Regional Options</guilabel> allow you to select the language for the Web Client (after logging into the system), and the language in which you will receive email notifications. In case of the Destkop Client, the language of the user interface depends on the program settings and do not change when you connect to a server. Use the WebIssues Settings command (see below) to change these settings.</para>

      <para>You can also select your preferred time zone. This setting determines the time zone for dates displayed in the Web Client, and for email notifications. However the Desktop Client always displays dates according to local time zone the computer on which it is running, and it does not take into account server settings or user preferences.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Regional options</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch03-fig25.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>The format in which numbers, dates and times are displayed, and the first day of the week in the calendar, depend on the current language of the user interface. You can change these settings using the <guilabel>Formats</guilabel> group of options. These changes will impact both the Web Client and the Desktop Client (after connecting to the specific server).</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Formats</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch03-fig26.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Using the <guilabel>Page Size</guilabel> options, you can specify the number of issues to be displayed on a single page in the list of issues, and the number of elements per page in the issue history. These options only affect the Web Client, because the Desktop Client always displays all issues and the entire history without pagination.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Page size</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch03-fig27.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>If the administrator of the WebIssues system enabled email notifications, you can also configure these notifications in the preferences window. For more information, see <xref linkend="webissues.track.alerts"/>.</para>

      <para>The system administrator can not only change the global settings, but also the individual settings for any user. To do this, open the list of user accounts, select the user whose settings you want to change, and use the <guilabel>User Preferences</guilabel> command.</para>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="webissues.work.personal.client">
      <title>Desktop Client settings</title>

      <para>To change the Desktop Client settings, click the little wrench icon in the right upper corner of the window. These settings do not depend on which WebIssues server you are connected to; they are stored on the local computer. You can change them even if you are not connected to any server.</para>

      <para>The first tab contains basic program settings:</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Basic settings</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch03-fig28.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>The <guilabel>Regional Settings</guilabel> allow you to select the language of the user interface for the Desktop Client. By default, it depends on the operating system settings. After changing the language you must close and restart the program.</para>

      <para>If you enable the <guilabel>Dock main window in system tray</guilabel> option, the program keeps running in the background even when you close the main window. You can always re-open this window by clicking on the icon in the system notifications area. To exit the program, instead of closing the window, click the <guibutton>Quit</guibutton> button, available in the upper right corner of the window when you enable this option.</para>

      <para>The <guilabel>Startup Options</guilabel> allow you to specify the behavior of the program when it is started. If the main window is docked, you can specify whether it is always visible at startup, always hidden, or either visible or hidden depending on its state when the program was closed. You can also specify whether the program should automatically connect to the last used server, display the server selection window, or connect only if it was connected when closing.</para>

      <para>In case of the Windows system, you can also specify whether the Desktop Client should be automatically run whenever you log into the system. This allows you to configure the program to be always running, connected to the server and instantly available.</para>

      <para>Use the <guilabel>Fonts</guilabel> options to change the fonts used in the comment editing window, and in the issue history view.</para>

      <para>If the <guilabel>Enable automatic checking for latest version</guilabel> option is active, the program will notify you if a newer version available. If you disable this option, you can still manually check if an update is available. To do this, open the window with information about the program. In the Web Client, click <guilabel>Tools</guilabel> and then <guilabel>About WebIssues</guilabel> if you are the system administrator. In the Desktop Client, click the question mark icon in the upper right corner of the window or press <shortcut><keycap>F1</keycap></shortcut>. Then click the <guibutton>Check Now</guibutton> button. If an update is available, you can open a page containing information about it, and also a page that allows you to download it.</para>

      <para>The second tab allows you to change more advanced settings of the Desktop Client:</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Advanced settings</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch03-fig29.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>The <guilabel>Behavior</guilabel> group of options allows you to select the default action when you click on a link to an attachment. By default the program will ask whether you want to open it using the default application, or save it in a selected location on the disk. You can also right-click on the link to quickly select the desired operation.</para>

      <para>The <guilabel>Update Intervals</guilabel> determine the intervals at which the program automatically retrieves data from the server (in minutes). The first interval determines how often the program updates the tree of projects and folders, lists of issues and the state of active alerts. The second interval specifies how often it updates issue types, views and other data that do not change very often.</para>

      <para>The <guilabel>Cache Settings</guilabel> options allow you to specify the maximum number of issues for which the full history is remembered (separately for each server), and the maximum total size of locally stored attachments for all servers.</para>

      <para>The <guilabel>Proxy Settings</guilabel> allow you to define the parameters of the proxy server, which will be used to connect to the WebIssues system. On Windows and OS X it will automatically detect your system settings, so manual configuration is usually not necessary. However, in case of Linux, you must enter the connection parameters if you want to use a proxy. If the proxy requires authentication, you will be prompted for a username and password when opening a connection.</para>

    </sect2>

  </sect1>

</chapter>
