<chapter id="webissues.track">
  <title>Tracking issues</title>

  <para>This chapter presents mechanisms that facilitate the cooperation of multiple users of the WebIssues system and effective communication in the team. Everyone who collaborates with other users of the system should read it.</para>

  <sect1 id="webissues.track.unread">
    <title>Unread issues</title>

    <para>Let's assume that in the Bugs folder there are two issues which we created in the previous chapter. In the meantime, another user logs onto the system, and adds a new comment to the <quote>Second issue</quote> and also creates a new <quote>Third issue</quote>.</para>

    <para>When you open the Bugs folder again, you will see the following situation:</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Status of issues</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch04-fig01.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The issue called <quote>Second issue</quote> has been marked with an icon of a green, closed envelope, because it's been modified since you last opened it. Not only new comments are marked in this way, but also all changes of attribute values ​​and new attachments, so you can keep track of what's happening with the issue.</para>

    <para>The issue called <quote>Third issue</quote> has been marked with a similar, yellow icon. It means that you've never opened it. Both issues are also marked with bold font.</para>

    <para>Click on the second issue to open it. Notice how the icon changes to an open envelope:</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Status of issues after openining</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch04-fig02.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The same will happen with the third issue, if you select it. The WebIssues system automatically marks all issues that you open as read. It also remembers the time when you open them &mdash; so if there are new changes, comments, etc., since that time, they will be marked with a green envelope again.</para>

    <para>You can also manually mark the selected issue as read or unread, using the <guilabel>Mark As Read</guilabel> and <guilabel>Mark As Unread</guilabel> commands. If you manually mark an issue as read, it will also change its state, once it's modified by another user.</para>

    <para>If you want to mark all issues in the current folder as read or unread, you can use the <guilabel>Mark All As Read</guilabel> and <guilabel>Mark As Unread</guilabel> commands. Remember that this will change the status all issues in the folder, not only those that are visible in the current view.</para>

    <note>
      <title>Note</title>
      <para>Unlike email, the status of each issue is stored by the system, regardless of which client application you are using and on which computer you run it.</para>
    </note>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="webissues.track.alerts">
    <title>Managing alerts</title>

    <para>Even if you are using views and automatic statuses of issues, it's not always visible at the first glance that there is a new or modified issue that requires your attention. Because of that, the WebIssues system has a mechanism of alerts, which are automatic notifications about unread issues that meet certain criteria.</para>

    <para>You can create an alert using any public or personal view, as well as the built-in <quote>All Issues</quote> view. Each alert is assigned to a specific folder.</para>

    <para>Suppose you want to keep an eye on active bugs and tasks which are assigned to you. Open the Bugs folder and select <guilabel>Manage Alerts</guilabel>. The list of alerts is initially empty, so choose <guilabel>Add Alert</guilabel> to define a new alert for this folder.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Adding an alert</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch04-fig03.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Select the <quote>Active Bugs</quote> view and click <guibutton>OK</guibutton>. The list now contains a new alert, and also displays the total number of all issues that meet the criteria of the view, and the number of unread and modified issues.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>List of alerts</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch04-fig04.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>If the alert contains unread issues, its icon will change to a closed, yellow envelope. Similarly, if it contains a modified issue, a green envelope will be displayed. So by opening the alerts window, you can quickly see if there are any issues which require your attention.</para>

    <para>Now repeat the same steps to create an <quote>Active Tasks</quote> alert in the Tasks folder. If you are using the Desktop Client, you will notice that the alerts are visible in the projects and folders tree:</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Tree with alerts</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch04-fig05.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The program periodically updates the contents of all folders for which you've defined alerts, so you can track their status almost in real time. If in any of the views there are some unread issues, the icon of the alert will be changed, its name will become bold, and the number of new and modified issues will appear in parentheses:</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Tree with active alerts</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch04-fig06.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>If you click on an alert in the tree, not only the folder, to which the selected alert belongs, will be opened, but also the view associated with this alert will be automatically selected. This mechanism is therefore very helpful in everyday work.</para>

    <tip>
      <title>Tip</title>
      <para>Create alerts only if you really needed them. A large number of alerts will distract your attention, and in addition will increase the time required to refresh all folders.</para>
    </tip>

    <para>If sending email notifications was enabled in the WebIssues system, you can configure the way of sending notifications for each alert.</para>

    <note>
      <title>Note</title>
      <para>For more information about setting up email notifications read the <xref linkend="webissues.prep.notifications"/> section.</para>
    </note>

    <para>There are three types of notifications available in the WebIssues system:</para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Immediate notifications</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Sent immediately when someone adds or changes an issue which meets the criteria of the alert.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Summary of notifications</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Sent at specified days and hours, if someone adds or changes issues related to the alert.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Summary reports</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Always sent at specified days and hours, regardless of whether any changes have occurred.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <para>How often immediate notifications are sent, depends on the configuration of cron job on the server. You can therefore receive them every few minutes or every hour.</para>

    <para>In order to receive notifications, you must change your user preferences. If you are using a browser, click <guilabel>Tools</guilabel> and then <guilabel>User Preferences</guilabel>. To change them in the Desktop Client, select <guilabel>User Preferences</guilabel> from the main window toolbar.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Notifications settings</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch04-fig07.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Enter a valid email to which the notifications will be sent. Select <guilabel>Do not include issues that I have already read</guilabel> if you don't want to receive notifications about issues that you've read (for example, if you created or modified them by yourself).</para>

    <para>Also set up the notifications schedule, by selecting days and hours at which the summary notification and summary reports will be sent. Depending on your needs, you can receive a summary once a week, several times a week, at a specified time every day, or several times a day.</para>

    <warning>
    <title>Warning</title>
    <para>You won't receive any notifications if you don't set the correct email address in your user preferences. You won't receive the summary emails, if you don't select any day or hour.</para>
    </warning>

    <para>The type of notification can be specified when you create an alert. You can also change it at any time for an existing alert. To do this, select the alert in the alert management window and select <guilabel>Edit Alert</guilabel>.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Changing an alert</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch04-fig08.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Immediate notifications are useful if you want to be kept informed of any changes, and you don't use the WebIssues system all the time. If an alert generates too many notifications, or if they are not very urgent, you can choose a summary of notifications instead, to receive aggregated information about recent changes, for example, once a day.</para>

    <para>Summary reports contain a list of all issues, regardless of whether they have been changed since the last notification, and whether they were read by you. They are useful if you want to track the status of all issues that meet specific criteria, for example, to check whether the active bugs are being solved continuously.</para>

    <para>All email notifications include the name of the associated project, folder and alert in the header, and also the list of issues. The list contains the same columns as the view which is associated with the alert.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>An email notification</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch04-fig09.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

  </sect1>

</chapter>
