<chapter id="webissues.track">
  <title>Tracking issues</title>

  <para>This chapter presents mechanisms that facilitate the cooperation of multiple users of the WebIssues system and effective communication in the team. Everyone who collaborates with other users of the system should read it.</para>

  <sect1 id="webissues.track.unread">
    <title>Unread issues</title>

    <para>Let's assume that in the Bugs folder there are two issues which we created in the previous chapter. In the meantime, another user logs onto the system, and adds a new comment to the <quote>Second issue</quote> and also creates a new <quote>Third issue</quote>.</para>

    <para>When you open the Bugs folder again, you will see the following situation:</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Status of issues</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch04-fig01.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The issue called <quote>Second issue</quote> has been marked with an icon of a green, closed envelope, because it's been modified since you last opened it. Not only new comments are marked in this way, but also all changes of attribute values ​​and new attachments, so you can keep track of what's happening with the issue.</para>

    <para>The issue called <quote>Third issue</quote> has been marked with a similar, yellow icon. It means that you've never opened it. Both issues are also marked with bold font.</para>

    <para>Click on the second issue to open it. Notice how the icon changes to an open envelope:</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Status of issues after opening</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch04-fig02.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The same will happen with the third issue, if you select it. The WebIssues system automatically marks all issues that you open as read. It also remembers the time when you open them &mdash; so if there are new changes, comments, etc., since that time, they will be marked with a green envelope again.</para>

    <para>You can also manually mark the selected issue as read or unread, using the <guilabel>Mark As Read</guilabel> and <guilabel>Mark As Unread</guilabel> commands. If you manually mark an issue as read, it will also change its state, once it's modified by another user.</para>

    <para>If you want to mark all issues in the current folder as read or unread, you can use the <guilabel>Mark All As Read</guilabel> and <guilabel>Mark As Unread</guilabel> commands. Remember that this will change the status all issues in the folder, not only those that are visible in the current view.</para>

    <note>
      <title>Note</title>
      <para>Unlike email, the status of each issue is stored by the system, regardless of which client application you are using and on which computer you run it.</para>
    </note>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="webissues.track.alerts">
    <title>Managing alerts</title>

    <para>Even if you are using views and unread statuses of issues, it's not always visible at the first glance that there is a new or modified issue that requires your attention. Because of that, the WebIssues system has a mechanism of alerts, which are automatic notifications about unread issues that meet certain criteria.</para>

    <para>You can create an alert using any public or personal view, as well as the built-in <quote>All Issues</quote> view. Each alert is assigned either to a specific folder or a global list of issues of a given type.</para>

    <para>Suppose you want to keep an eye on all active bugs and tasks. Open the Bugs folder and select <guilabel>Manage Alerts</guilabel>. The list of alerts is initially empty, so choose <guilabel>Add Alert</guilabel> to define a new alert for this folder.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Adding an alert</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch04-fig03.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Select the <quote>Active Bugs</quote> view and click <guibutton>OK</guibutton>. The list now contains a new alert, and also displays the total number of all issues that meet the criteria of the view, and the number of unread and modified issues.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>List of alerts</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch04-fig04.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>If the alert contains unread issues, its icon will change to a closed, yellow envelope. Similarly, if it contains a modified issue, a green envelope will be displayed. So by opening the alerts window, you can quickly see if there are any issues which require your attention.</para>

    <para>Now repeat the same steps to create an <quote>Active Tasks</quote> alert in the Tasks folder. If you are using the Desktop Client, you will notice that the alerts are visible in the projects and folders tree:</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Tree with alerts</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch04-fig05.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The program periodically updates the contents of all folders for which you've defined alerts, so you can track their status almost in real time. If in any of the views there are some unread issues, the icon of the alert will be changed, its name will become bold, and the number of new and modified issues will appear in parentheses:</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Tree with active alerts</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch04-fig06.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>If you click on an alert in the tree, not only the folder, to which the selected alert belongs, will be opened, but also the view associated with this alert will be automatically selected. This mechanism is therefore very helpful in everyday work.</para>

    <sect2 id="webissues.track.alerts.notifications">
      <title>Email notifications</title>

      <para>If sending emails was enabled in the WebIssues system, you can configure the way of sending notifications for each alert.</para>

      <note>
        <title>Note</title>
        <para>For more information about configuring sending emails read <xref linkend="webissues.prep.notifications"/>.</para>
      </note>

      <para>There are three types of notifications available in the WebIssues system:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Immediate notifications</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Sent immediately when someone adds or changes an issue which meets the criteria of the alert.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Summary of notifications</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Sent at specified days and hours, if someone adds or changes issues related to the alert.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Summary reports</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Always sent at specified days and hours, regardless of whether any changes have occurred.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <para>The type of notification can be specified when you create an alert, as long as sending emails is enabled on the server. You can also change it at any time for an existing alert. To do this, select the alert in the alert management window and select <guilabel>Modify Alert</guilabel>.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Changing an alert</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch04-fig08.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Immediate notifications are useful if you want to be kept informed of any changes, and you don't use the WebIssues system all the time. The frequency of sending immediate notifications depends on the configuration of cron job on the server. It can vary from once in a few minutes to once an hour. If an alert generates too many notifications, or if they are not very urgent, you can choose a summary of notifications instead, to receive aggregated information about recent changes, for example, once a day.</para>

      <para>Summary reports contain a list of all issues, regardless of whether they have been changed since the last notification, and whether they were read by you. They are useful if you want to track the status of all issues that meet specific criteria, for example, to check whether the active bugs are being solved continuously.</para>

      <para>Summary notifications and reports are sent at the selected days and hours. Depending on your needs, you can receive a summary email once a week, several times a week, once a day, or several times a day. You must select at least one day and one hours when configuring a summary email.</para>

      <note>
        <title>Note</title>
        <para>In version 1.0 the summary schedule was configured globally in the user preferences. When updating to version 1.1, the schedule settings are automatically migrated to individual summary alerts.</para>
      </note>

      <para>In order to receive notifications, you must change your user preferences. If you are using a browser, click <guilabel>Tools</guilabel> and then <guilabel>User Preferences</guilabel>. To change them in the Desktop Client, select <guilabel>User Preferences</guilabel> from the main window toolbar.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Notifications settings</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch04-fig07.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Enter a valid email to which the notifications will be sent. Select <guilabel>Include issue details in notifications and summary reports</guilabel>, if you want the emails to contain also issue details and the history of changes and recently added comments and attachments. Otherwise only a summary of issues will be sent.</para>

      <para>Select <guilabel>Do not notify about issues that I have already read</guilabel> if you don't want to receive notifications about issues that you've read (for example, if you created or modified them by yourself). Also issue details that you've read, will not be included in that case. This option doesn't affect summary reports, which always contain all issues and changes.</para>

      <warning>
        <title>Warning</title>
        <para>You won't receive any notifications if you don't set the correct email address in your user preferences.</para>
      </warning>

      <para>All email notifications include the name of the associated project, folder and alert in the header, and also the list of issues. The list contains the same columns as the view which is associated with the alert.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>An email notification</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch04-fig09.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>If you selected the appropriate option, email notifications will also include details of each issue, similar to the issue details view in the main window of the program.</para>

      <tip>
        <title>Tip</title>
        <para>Instead of configuring a separate alert for each folder of a given type, it may be more convenient to create a single alert associated with a global list of issues. To create and manage global alerts, open the global list of the appropriate type and select the <guilabel>Manage Alerts</guilabel> command. An additional advantage is that only a single email notification is sent containing all new and modified issues, instead of separate emails for each folder.</para>
      </tip>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="webissues.track.alerts.public">
      <title>Public alerts</title>

      <para>Project administrators and system administrators have the ability to create public alerts which are shared by all users. For example, if you want all users to keep track of active bugs assigned to them in a specified folder, open the folder, select <guilabel>Manage Alerts</guilabel> and then select <guilabel>Add Public Alert</guilabel>. Choose the <quote>My Active Bugs</quote> view from the list and click <guibutton>OK</guibutton>.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>List of alerts with a public alert</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch04-fig09-01.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>All users will now see the alert in their project tree in the Desktop Client. Public alerts can be distinguished from personal alerts by a small user symbol in the corner of the icon.</para>

      <para>You can configure email type and schedule for a public alert in order to enable sending email notifications. Notifications for public alerts associated with a folder are sent to all users who can access the folder, regardless of whether or not they are explicitly listed as project members. If the folder belongs to a public project, notifications are sent to all active users. Notifications for public alerts associated with a global list of issues are sent to all active users who have access to at least one folder of the given type. Only users who have a valid email address configured in their user preferences will receive email notifications.</para>

      <note>
        <title>Note</title>
        <para>Summary notifications for public alerts are always sent according to the server's time zone, and the time zone preferences of individual users are ignored. However, other preferences, such as including issue details in notifications and summary reports and ignoring notifications notify about issues that the user has already read, are respected for each individual user.</para>
      </note>

      <para>A public alert can be associated either with a public view or the <quote>All Issues</quote> view. It cannot be associated with a personal view; you have to publish the view first to make it available to all users.</para>

      <para>Regular users are not allowed to delete or modify settings of a public alert. Also they cannot create a personal alert associated with the same view as the already existing public alert. When a public alert is created, all personal alerts associated with the same view are deleted.</para>

      <tip>
        <title>Tip</title>
        <para>Setting up a large number of public alerts may cause a lot of emails to be generated. You can restrict the number of emails by using appropriate view conditions; for example users can only receive notifications about issues which are currently assigned to them. Use global alerts when possible, instead of creating separate alerts for each folder. Also consider using summary notifications instead of immediate notifications.</para>
      </tip>

    </sect2>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="webissues.track.subscriptions">
    <title>Subscriptions</title>

    <para>While alerts make it possible to receive notifications about multiple issues from a specific folder, subscriptions allow receiving email notifications about individual selected issues. You can subscribe to any issue you have access to using the <guilabel>Subscribe</guilabel> command in the issue details view. A subscribed issue has a small green arrow in the bottom right corner of its icon. To cancel a subscription for selected issue, use the <guilabel>Unsubscribe</guilabel> command. Note that subscriptions are only available when sending emails is enabled on the server. Also you need to set up a valid email address in your user preferences.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Subscribed issues</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch04-fig10.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>Once an issue is subscribed, you will receive an email whenever someone modifies it by editing its attributes, adding or modifying its description, adding a comment or attachment. The email will always contain the details of the changes, regardless of the notification settings in your user preferences. Also the read or unread state of the issue is ignored. You will receive a subscription notification even if you read the issue before the email is sent. However, changes made by you, including your own comments and attachments, will not be included in the subscription notifications.</para>

    <para>You can use a combination of alert notifications and subscription, depending on your needs. Although alerts and subscriptions are similar concepts, there are a few important differences:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Alert notifications can be sent as immediate notifications, summary notifications or summary reports. Subscription notifications are always sent immediately after a change is made, i.e. as frequent as the cron job runs on the server.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Alert notifications are sent for all issues in a folder, or all issues matching certain criteria, for example assigned to you or created by you. This way you don't have to manually mark individual issues that you want to receive notifications for. On the other hand, subscriptions make it possible for you to select individual issues that you want to be notified about.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>Depending on the preferences, alert notifications can contain only a list of issues, or also the details of recent modifications of the issues. Subscription notifications always include the detailed modifications.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>You can configure alert notifications to only be sent for unread issues and changes. On the other hand, subscriptions will only include changes made by other users, regardless of the read state of the issue.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Subscriptions are also very useful in connection with the email inbox feature, because the email senders can be automatically subscribed to created issues. This even allows external users to subscribe to issues and receive notifications. For more information, see <xref linkend="webissues.prep.inbox" />.</para>

  </sect1>

</chapter>
