<chapter id="webissues.admin">
  <title>System administration</title>

  <para>This chapter describes topics related to the administration of projects and users, and system maintenance.</para>

  <sect1 id="webissues.admin.panel">
    <title>Administration panel</title>

    <para>Most of the activities related to the administration, maintenance and configuration of the system can be performed through the Administration Panel. The exceptions are operations associated with projects and folders management, which can be performed directly in the main window.</para>

    <para>To access the Administration Panel in the Web Client, click <guilabel>Administration Panel</guilabel> in the upper right corner of the window. This option is available only to users with server administrator privileges.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>The Administration Panel</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch05-fig01.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The Administration Panel is divided into the following modules:</para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>General Information</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Displays information about the WebIssues server, the database and the environment in which the server is running. See <xref linkend="webissues.admin.info"/>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Event Log</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Allows viewing events from the event log of the WebIssues server. See <xref linkend="webissues.admin.log"/>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Server Settings</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Allows configuring the language settings, and other settings of the WebIssues server. See <xref linkend="webissues.custom.locale"/> and <xref linkend="webissues.custom.settings"/>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Email Settings</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Allows configuring the settings of notification emails . See <xref linkend="webissues.prep.notifications"/>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>User Accounts</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Allows managing user accounts of the WebIssues server. See <xref linkend="webissues.admin.users"/>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Registration Requests</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Allows approving or rejecting user registration requests. This module is available only if user registration was enabled in server settings. See <xref linkend="webissues.admin.register"/>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
      <term>Issue Types</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Allows customizing issue types and public views. See <xref linkend="webissues.custom.types"/> and <xref linkend="webissues.custom.views"/>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <para>In the Desktop Client it is possible to administer users and projects and and to manage issue types and views. The <guilabel>Users</guilabel> and <guilabel>Types</guilabel> commands are available directly from the main window's toolbar. However, the full Administration Panel is not available. In order to access the event log or change system settings, you must therefore use the Web Client.</para>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="webissues.admin.info">
    <title>Server information</title>

    <para>In order to display general information about the server, go to the Administration Panel and click <guilabel>General Information</guilabel>.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>General information</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch05-fig02.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>You will see the version number of the currently installed database schema, the name of the server and its unique identifier. You can use the <guilabel>Rename Server</guilabel> command to change the name of the server, which is visible in the upper left corner of the Web Client and in the title bar of both client programs. With the <guilabel>Generate New Unique ID</guilabel> command you can change the identifier of the server to a new, randomly generated identifier.</para>

    <note>
      <title>Note</title>
      <para>The unique identifier allows the Desktop Client to distinguish individual instances of the WebIssues server, regardless of their name and URL. It is automatically generated during the installation, and normally there is no need to change it. Changing this identifier may be needed when a server instance is cloned (for example, when an update is tested on a temporary copy before deploying to production environment), and also after manually making changes to the database (for example, when you restore a previous version of the database from the backup).</para>
    </note>

    <para>In the next part of the window you can see basic information about your server: the name of the instance (usually it will be <literal>default</literal>, unless you created multiple instances of the server within a single installation), the base URL of the server and the path of the directory where the configuration file is located. Also there is the version of PHP, the web server and the operating system, and the name of the computer on which WebIssues is installed.</para>

    <para>You can also see information about the type and version of the database server, the name of the host and the database, and an optional prefix for table names in the database.</para>

    <para>The last part of the window contains information about the last execution of the cron job. For more information, see <xref linkend="webissues.prep.nofitications.cron"/>.</para>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="webissues.admin.log">
    <title>Event log</title>

    <para>To view the event log of the WebIssues server, go to the Administration Panel and click <guilabel>Event Log</guilabel>.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>The event log</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch05-fig03.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The event log contains information about errors, access to the system, important administrative operations and cron job executions. It is independent from the logs of PHP, the web server and the operating system. Its purpose is to supplement those information, not to replace them. In particular, some serious errors (such as lack of access to the database) can not be stored in the event log of the WebIssues server.</para>

    <para>Events in the event log are divided into four types:</para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Errors</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Errors and warnings in the system WebIssues. They may result from incorrect input data, lack of permission to perform some operations, conflicts between parallel changes or incorrect system configuration.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Access</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Information about successful and failed attempts to log into the system, as well as errors associated with the denial of access to specific pages or operations.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Audit</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Information about important administrative operations, such as: creating and changing passwords or permissions of users, creating, deleting and modifying issue types, attributes, projects and folders, and deleting issues.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Cron</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Information about executions of the cron job. For more information, see <xref linkend="webissues.prep.nofitications.cron"/>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <para>Events also have three different levels of severity: information, warning and error. They are marked with different icons.</para>

    <para>By default, the log displays all events, sorted from newest to oldest. If you are interested only in a specific type of events, click on one of the options in the upper right corner of the window to enable filtering.</para>

    <para>Click on an event to view detailed information about it. In addition to the type, severity and full message, also the name of the user who performed the operation and the host name or IP address, from which the connection was made, are displayed.</para>

    <note>
      <title>Note</title>
      <para>Although detailed information about errors are stored in the event log, for security reasons they are not displayed on error pages. However, you can enable detailed error messages for development or troubleshooting purposes. You can also enable an additional text log which makes debugging easier. However, you should not enable those settings in production environment. For more information, please visit <ulink url="http://wiki.mimec.org/wiki/WebIssues/Configuration"/>.</para>
    </note>

    <para>Events are automatically removed from the log after a specified amount of time. For more information about configuring this period, refer to <xref linkend="webissues.custom.settings"/>.</para>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="webissues.admin.users">
    <title>Managing users</title>

    <para>Managing users in the WebIssues system includes the creation of user accounts, managing global rights of users, and giving users access to specific projects.</para>

    <sect2 id="webissues.admin.users.accounts">
      <title>User accounts</title>

      <para>To manage the users of WebIssues system, go to the Administration Panel and click <guilabel>User Accounts</guilabel>. In case of the Desktop Client, use the <guilabel>Users</guilabel> command from the main window toolbar.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>User accounts</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch05-fig04.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Each user has a unique, fixed login, which is used along with the password when logging into the system. Each user also has a name that is visible to other users and that can be changed by the administrator if necessary. Depending on the convention, it can be the first and last name, the email address, or any other name.</para>

      <para>Managing privileges in the WebIssues system is relatively simple. There are three global access levels:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>System administrator</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Users with this level have access to all functions of the Administration Panel. They can manage user accounts and customize the issue types and public views. They are also members and administrators of all existing projects in the system, even if they are not explicitly granted such permissions. The first such account is created upon installation.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Regular user</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Users with this level of access can log into the system and change their personal settings. They can access only those projects to which they were granted specific privileges. They can be administrators of selected projects, but they can't create new projects.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Disabled</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Users with this level of access are not allowed to log into the system and do not have access to any part of it.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <para>To create a new user account, select <guilabel>Add User</guilabel>.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Creating a user account</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch05-fig05.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Enter the name of the user, the login and initial password. To avoid mistakes, you must enter the password twice. You can select <guilabel>User must change password at next logon</guilabel> to force the user to change password when logging into the system for the first time.</para>

      <para>If the user doesn't remember their password, you can reset it by selecting the user from the list and clicking <guilabel>Change Password</guilabel>. You will be asked to enter a new password twice. Also in this case you can select <guilabel>User must change password at next logon</guilabel>.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Changing user's password</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch05-fig06.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>When you're changing your own password, for greater security you must also enter your current password. All users can also change their own password at any time, using the <guilabel>Change Password</guilabel> command, which is available in the <guilabel>Tools</guilabel> window or in the toolbar of the Desktop Client main window.</para>

      <note>
        <title>Note</title>
        <para>If you forget the system administrator's password, you cann't easily recover it. All passwords are stored in a database as secure hashes, and it's practically impossible to recreate the original password. However, if you have  access to the database, you can reset the administrator's password, by generating a new hash and storing it in the <literal>user_passwd</literal> column for the corresponding user in the <literal>users</literal> table. WebIssues uses the <quote>Portable PHP password hashing framework</quote>, which is compatible with such programs as Wordpress or Drupal, so you can use one of the available <ulink url="http://scriptserver.mainframe8.com/wordpress_password_hasher.php">hash generators</ulink> for these programs.</para>
      </note>

      <para>To change the global access level of a user, select that user on the list and click <guilabel>Change Access</guilabel>. Then choose the new access level and click <guibutton>OK</guibutton>. You can't deprive your own administrator right, because the system must have at least one active administrator account.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Changing user's access</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch05-fig07.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>To change the name of a user, select that user on the list and click <guilabel>Rename User</guilabel>. Enter a new name and click <guibutton>OK</guibutton>.</para>

      <tip>
        <title>Tip</title>
        <para>Avoid changing the names of users who have assigned issues. Attribute values ​​are stored as text, so changing the user name will not automatically change the values ​​of <quote>Assigned to</quote> attributes. This may cause the user to no longer see those assigned issues.</para>
      </tip>

      <para>To manage the list of projects available for the selected user, use the <guilabel>User Projects</guilabel> command. You can also manage the list of users who have access to the selected project. For more information, please refer to <xref linkend="webissues.admin.users.members"/>.</para>

      <para>You can also change the preferences of any user using the <guilabel>User Preferences</guilabel> command. All users can also change their own settings, using the <guilabel>User Prererences</guilabel> command in the <guilabel>Tools</guilabel> window or in the toolbar of the Desktop Client main window. For more information about user preferences, see <xref linkend="webissues.work.personal"/>.</para>

      <para>The WebIssues system does not allow to delete existing users, because it keeps all the historical information; for example, changes made by individual users. Instead, you can change the access level of users to disabled, when they should no longer be able to use the system. Use the filtering options in the upper right corner of the list to hide disabled user accounts.</para>

      <para>The WebIssues system allows users to register new accounts by themselves. In this case it is necessary for the system administrator to the approve registration requests. For more information, see <xref linkend="webissues.admin.register"/> and <xref linkend="webissues.custom.settings"/>.</para>

    </sect2>

    <sect2 id="webissues.admin.users.members">
      <title>Project members</title>

      <para>A newly created user has no access to any project, unless he is the system administrator. To manage user privileges for specific projects, go to <guilabel>Manage Projects</guilabel> from the main window, select the project, and then click <guilabel>Project Members</guilabel>. In case of the Desktop Client, this command is available directly from the main window if you activate the projects tree.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>List of project members</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch05-fig08.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>There are two levels of access to projects:</para>

      <variablelist>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Project administrator</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Users with this level of access can manage members and folders of the project. They can also delete or move issues and edit and delete all comments and attachments within the project.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
        <varlistentry>
          <term>Regular member</term>
          <listitem>
            <para>Users with this level of access can view issues in all folders, manage their own alerts, and create new issues and edit existing ones. They can also add comments and attachments, and edit and delete their own comments and attachments.</para>
          </listitem>
        </varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <para>The global access level is always more important than permissions for a given project. A system administrator automatically becomes the administrator of all projects, and a disabled user has no access to any project. Regular users only have access to projects that they are members of, according to the permissions that were assigned to them.</para>

      <para>To add members of the project, select <guilabel>Add Members</guilabel>.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Adding project members</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch05-fig09.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>Select one or more users who are not yet members of the project. Then select the appropriate level of access and click <guibutton>OK</guibutton>.</para>

      <para>To change the access level of a member, select the member on the list and click <guilabel>Change Access</guilabel>. Then select the new access level and click <guibutton>OK </guibutton>. You can't deprive your own project administrator rights, unless you are a system administrator.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>Changing member's access</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch05-fig10.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>To remove a member of the project, select the member on the list and click <guilabel>Remove Member</guilabel>. In case of the Desktop Client, you can choose several members on the list, and change their access level or remove them from the project simultaneously.</para>

      <para>You can also view a list of available projects for the selected user, as well as to add a user to the selected projects, remove and change the access level. It is especially useful when creating new user accounts. However, unlike the project members management function, it is available only to system administrators.</para>

      <para>To manage user projects, go to the Administration Panel and click and click <guilabel>User Accounts</guilabel>. In the Desktop Client, use the <guilabel>Users</guilabel> command from the toolbar of the main window. Then select the user from the list and click <guilabel>User Projects</guilabel>. The list of user projects is analogous to the list of project members.</para>

      <figure>
        <title>List of user projects</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch05-fig10-01.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>To add a user to some projects, use the <guilabel>Add Projects</guilabel> command. Select one or more projects, choose the appropriate access level and click <guibutton>OK</guibutton>. To change the access level to a project, select a project from the list and click <guilabel>Change Access</guilabel>. Then choose the new access level and click <guibutton>OK</guibutton>. To remove a user from a project, select it from the list and click <guilabel>Remove Project</guilabel>. In the Desktop Client, you can select several projects at once and change or remove access to them.</para>

    </sect2>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="webissues.admin.register">
    <title>Registration requests</title>

    <para>The WebIssues system administator can enable an option that allows users to register new accounts. A new user has to provide the name, login and password, and the email address, which is verified by sending an activation message. Active registration requests must then be approved by the administrator. Also the projets that the new user has access must be specified. Only then the user will be able to log into the system.</para>

    <note>
      <title>Note</title>
      <para>For more information about user registration, please refer to <xref linkend="webissues.work.login"/>. You will find more information about enabling and configuring the user registration module in <xref linkend="webissues.custom.settings"/>.</para>
    </note>

    <para>To see active registration requests, that awail approval, go to the Administration Panel and click <guilabel>Registration Requests</guilabel>. This function is not available in the Desktop Client.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Registration requests</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch05-fig10-02.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>To approve a registration request, select it from the list, and use the <guilabel>Approve Request</guilabel> command. Select the projects to which the user will have access and click <guibutton>OK</guibutton>. The registration request will disappear from the list, and a new user will appear in the list of user accounts, where you can change the name, access level, settings and password, just like for accounts created directly by the admininistrator. The user will also receive an email notification that the request was approved.</para>

    <para>To reject the selected registration request, use the <guilabel>Reject Request</guilabel> command. The request will be removed from the list, and the user will receive an email notification that the request was rejected.</para>

    <para>If you want to receive automatic notifications about new registration requests that are waiting for approval, enter your e-mail in <xref linkend="webissues.custom.settings">the server settings</xref>.</para>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="webissues.admin.projects">
    <title>Managing projects</title>

    <para>If you are using the Desktop Client, you can manage projects and folders directly from the main window of the program. The relevant commands are available if you activate the project tree by clicking on it. In case of the Web Client, select the <guilabel>Manage Projects</guilabel> command, located above the projects tree, to manage projects and folders.</para>

    <para>If you are a system administrator, you can manage all projects and create new projects. If you are the administrator of a project, you can manage its members and folders.</para>

    <para>To add a new project, select <guilabel>Add Project</guilabel>, enter the name and optional description of the project and click <guibutton>OK</guibutton>.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Creating a project</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch05-fig11.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>After creating a new project, no regular user has access to it. For more information on granting users access to projects, see <xref linkend="webissues.admin.users.members"/>.</para>

    <para>The system administrator can change the name of any project. To do this, select the project and click <guilabel>Rename Project</guilabel>. You can also delete projects using the <guilabel>Delete Project</guilabel> command. If the project is not empty, a warning will be displayed.</para>

    <warning>
      <title>Warning</title>
      <para>When deleting projects or folders, pay special attention whether you are not mistakenly deleting the wrong data. All issues contained in them are permanently and irreversibly removed from the system, and it's not possible to restore them.</para>
    </warning>

    <para>The project description is displayed when the project is selected in the projects tree in both the Web Client and the Desktop Client. It can be used to provide information about the project, including links to important issues or external resources. Both system administrators and project administrators can add a description to an existing project, edit the description and delete it. Project descriptions use the same format as issue descriptions and comments; see <xref linkend="webissues.work.issues.comments"/> for more information.</para>

    <para>To add a new folder, select a project and click <guilabel>Add Folder</guilabel>.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Creating a folder</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject><imagedata fileref="images/ch05-fig12.png" format="PNG"/></imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>When creating a folder, you have to give it a name that is unique within the project and select the type of issues that will be stored in it. After creating a folder its type can't be changed. However, you can rename a folder using the <guilabel>Rename Folder</guilabel> command and delete it using the <guilabel>Delete Folder</guilabel> command.</para>

    <para>You can also move a folder from one project to another. In order to do this, you must be the administrator of the system or of both projects &mdash; the source one and destination one. Select the folder you want to move and click <guilabel>Move Folder</guilabel>. Then select the destination project from the list and click <guibutton>OK</guibutton>.</para>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="webissues.admin.updating">
    <title>Updating the system</title>

    <para>One of the maintenance tasks is updating the WebIssues system to a newer version. New versions fix potential problems and add new features, so it is recommended to periodically update the software. To quickly check if a newer version of the system is available, click <guilabel>Tools</guilabel> and <guilabel>About WebIssues</guilabel>, and then in the <guilabel>Latest Version</guilabel> group, click the <guibutton>Check</guibutton> button. The Desktop Client by default automatically checks if a new version is available (see <xref linkend="webissues.work.personal.client"/>).</para>

    <para>Before the update, it is recommended to back up the database and WebIssues system files, and also disable the web server to prevent other users from accessing the system during the update.</para>

    <note>
      <title>Note</title>
      <para>If you cannot disable the server or block access to it, you can also temporarily rename the <literal>config.inc.php</literal> configuration file, which by default is located in the <literal>data/sites/default</literal> subdirectory. You may even completely remove the file, and then recreate it using the installer, because at the time of installation the existing database will be preserved and automatically updated to the new version.</para>
    </note>

    <para>First, delete all files and subdirectories from the directory where you installed the WebIssues server, remembering to keep the <literal>data</literal> subdirectory, which stores all files related to the particular installation; for example, configuration files and attachments of issues. If you created your own <literal>.htaccess</literal> file or <literal>web.config</literal> file (in case of IIS), then also make a copy of it to be able to restore it later.</para>

    <para>Download and unpack the new WebIssues server package &mdash; it contains a directory named <literal>webissues-x.y</literal> (where <literal>x.y</literal> is the version of the package). Then move all files and subdirectories from that directory to the directory where the WebIssues server was previously installed.</para>

    <para>After copying the files, enable the web server and open the main page of the WebIssues system in the browser. If there is a need to update the database, a message will be displayed. You will be asked to enter the login and password of the WebIssues system administrator, and then the database will be updated to the current version. Otherwise, the system is immediately ready to work.</para>

    <para>It is also recommended to update the Desktop Client to a newer version on the computers of all people who use it. Generally, however, the Desktop Client can communicate with both older and newer version of the server, provided that the first two digits of the version number is the same. Therefore, client version 1.0 will not work with the 1.1 system, and client version 1.1 will not work with the 1.0 system, but both versions can be installed side by side on a single computer.</para>

    <note>
      <title>Note</title>
      <para>Versions marked as <literal>beta</literal> are the so-called developer versions. They allow for testing new features before the official version is released, but it is not recommended to use them for production purposes. Development versions of the system can only be used with the same version of the Desktop Client. It is possible to update from a production version to a newer development version (for example, from 1.0.5 to 1.1-beta1), and from the production version to the final production version (for example, from 1.1-beta1 to 1.1).</para>
    </note>

    <para>When updating the server from version 1.0 to version 1.1, the first comment of each issue will be automatically converted to its description, but only if it was created by the person who created the issue and no more than 15 minutes after creating it. You may review the issues after the update and change the descriptions if necessary. Note that all comments and descriptions updated from version 1.0 will use the plain text format, but you can change the format when editing them.</para>

    <para>In order to update the server from version 0.8.5, you must first install version 1.0 of the server and select the option to import existing data from version 0.8.5. Then you can update the server from version 1.0 to 1.1.</para>

  </sect1>

</chapter>
