<preface id="webissues.preface">
  <title>Preface</title>

  <sect1 id="webissues.preface.about">
    <title>About the book</title>

    <para>This book is intended for users and administrators of the WebIssues team collaboration system. It was written both for people who have never used any issue tracking software and team collaboration support systems, as well as those who already have experience with similar software.</para>

    <para>This guide was written by the creator of WebIssues, taking into account questions and comments raised by users over several years of development of this system. My goal was to create the most useful and helpful documentation. Therefore, unlike the previous version, this book focuses more on the most commonly performed tasks and not on describing the various windows and functions.</para>

    <para>Just as the entire WebIssues system, this book is licensed under a free license, which means that it can be freely modified and redistributed. I encourage you to send comments and suggestions for improvement.</para>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="webissues.preface.howtoread">
    <title>How to read this book</title>

    <para>If you are responsible for the administration and implementation of the system, you should generally read this book sequentially, from the beginning to the end, because it will guide you through the entire process of preparing the system and successively introduce various aspects of the use and administration of the system.</para>

    <para>End users should primarily read <xref linkend="webissues.intro"/>, <xref linkend="webissues.work"/> and <xref linkend="webissues.track"/>, which introduce the basics of working with the WebIssues system.</para>

    <para>If you are an advanced user and want to start working immediately, you can read this book in whatever order. To get information about the topic you are interested in, use the Table of Contents included at the beginning of this book.</para>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="webissues.preface.conventions">
    <title>Used conventions</title>

    <para>To facilitate reading this book, the following typographical conventions are used:</para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><firstterm>Term</firstterm></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>First use of a term with its definition.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><guilabel>Name</guilabel></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Name of a user interface element – window, button, label, etc.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><filename>File</filename></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Name of a file or directory.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>	

    <para>Some information has been placed in special boxes:</para>

    <tip>
      <title>Tip</title>
      <para>Useful information, hint, or recommended practice.</para>
    </tip>

    <warning>
      <title>Warning</title>
      <para>Important information which requires special attention.</para>
    </warning>

    <note>
      <title>Note</title>
      <para>Additional information intended mostly for advanced users.</para>
    </note>

  </sect1>

  <sect1 id="webissues.preface.organization">
    <title>Organization of the book</title>

    <para>The following is a list of chapters of this book and their contents:</para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><xref linkend="webissues.intro"/></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Explains the basics of issues tracking and team collaboration. Describes the organization of data in the WebIssues system and presents the life cycle of example issues.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><xref linkend="webissues.prep"/></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Describes step by step the process of installing a new system and preparing it to work.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><xref linkend="webissues.work"/></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Introduces the basics of individual work with the system &mdash; creating and editing issues and searching for information.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><xref linkend="webissues.track"/></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Presents the way of collaboration of many users of the system and effective communication in the team.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><xref linkend="webissues.admin"/></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Describes topics related to the administration of projects and users, and system maintenance.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><xref linkend="webissues.custom"/></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Describes how to configure and customize the system to suit your needs for advanced administrators.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><xref linkend="webissues.resources"/></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Presents a list of additional sources of information about the WebIssues system.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term><xref linkend="webissues.licenses"/></term>
        <listitem>
          <para>Contains copies of the licenses of the program and this book.</para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>	

  </sect1>

</preface>
